<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advice to apprentices, and other young persons, to beware of evil company and evil courses and particularly of theft. By William Smythies curate of St. Giles Cripplegate. Licensed and entred according to order.</title>
            <author>Smythies, William, d. 1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833659</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833659</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60680)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2177:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Advice to apprentices, and other young persons, to beware of evil company and evil courses and particularly of theft. By William Smythies curate of St. Giles Cripplegate. Licensed and entred according to order.</title>
                  <author>Smythies, William, d. 1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by and for T. Milbourn in Jewen-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Price two-pence.</note>
                  <note>Marked, stained and torn, wth some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38137:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Advice to Apprentices,</hi> And other Young Perſons, To beware of Evil Company and Evil Courſes: And particularly of <hi>THEFT.</hi> By <hi>William Smythies</hi> Curate of St. <hi>Giles Cripplegate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Licenſed and Entred according to Order.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by and for <hi>T. Milbourn</hi> in <hi>Jewen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet.</hi> 1687.</p>
            <p>Price Two-pence.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38137:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38137:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:38137:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38137:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ADVICE TO YOUNG PERSO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE fearful Calamities which vicious young Perſons bring upon themſelves and others, by their Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; their deplorable Condition whilſt they live, and when they dye, (which I have frequently, with a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful Heart, obſerved) is the Occaſion of this, and may be of ſome other ſuch Little and Cheap Publications.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is by the Wickedneſs and Ungodlineſs of young Perſons, that the Devil <hi>exalts his Kingdom</hi> in the World, and makes it to be a Plantation or Nurſery for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in which <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Vice</hi> ſhall grow, and <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> be depreſt. It is by <hi>their</hi> caſting off the Fear of God, that he hopes to eſtabliſh his Throne, from Generation to Generation; well knowing, that it is the beſt Security which he can have, that their Poſterity (like their Parents) will make haſte to become his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Servants. Nothing Ruines the World, and brings ſo much Miſery into it, as the Miſcarriages of thoſe that are young. No Man can undertake to tell the Miſchief which <hi>One</hi> of that Age may bring upon himſelf and others, before he dyes: Nor can the young Man himſelf foretell it. There are many that are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of notorious Outrages, and moſt deſtructive Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; of which, if they had been told when they were young, they would have ſaid to ſuch a Prophet as <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zael</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:38137:4"/>did; <hi>Am I a Dog, that I ſhould do this thing?</hi> Who can tell into what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y and Wickedneſs <hi>he</hi> will run, who <hi>enters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the deſtroyer,</hi> when he ſhould be <hi>remembring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were a very happy thing if young Perſons would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by the Commands of God, who ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of our Years, though not of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Scripture which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of God, concerning early <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt part, wholly loſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> enough; and afterwards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> concern'd in them.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe who dare not diſobey the Commands of their Parents or Maſters, for fear of preſent Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, make light of diſobeying the great God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though eternal Puniſhment be the conſequence of it.</p>
            <p>It were likewiſe very Happy, if the Advantages of a pious and virtuous Life would prevail with young Perſons. Nothing is more acknowledged (and yet leſs practiced) than that which the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.27. <hi>It is good for a Man that he bear the yoke in his Youth.</hi> No Man begins to live, till he begins to live well. The Prodigal in the Parable was dead whilſt he lived a <hi>riotous</hi> life: <hi>This my Son was dead,</hi> &amp;c. No man begins to be Happy, till he begins to be Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, becauſe he knows that he is wrong and out of the <hi>way of Peace.</hi> There is continued Fear and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity of mind upon every ſerious thought; and no man can deny but there is juſt cauſe for it. All Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners acknowledge, in the time of their Diſtreſs and real ſenſibility of their condition, that they never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed any true Pleaſure or Satisfaction, becauſe <hi>their minds were not ſubject to the Law of God</hi> out diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to it: And therefore thoſe that often ſaw their merry Faces, did not ſee how <hi>ſorrowful their Hearts were in the midſt of mirth;</hi> nor how many gripes they had in their minds, to think of their condition. <hi>The
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38137:4"/>young man that fears God, and lives a ſober and a godly life, hath more pleaſure in one day, than the vitious and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient can have in the longeſt Age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this ſhall not be my preſent ſubject, though it would be a very pleaſant one; becauſe the Perverſe and Stubborn Nature of Man is not ſo apt to be drawn as driven to that which is good: And the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of preſent Miſeries in this life, which are the Objects of ſence, are more apt to prevail, than the eternal Miſeries of the life to come, which are the Objects of Faith. I ſhall therefore conſider ſome of the intolerable Miſeries which young Perſons bring upon themſelves, which they little foreſee, when they begin to allow themſelves in the neglect of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to God and men.</p>
            <p>We live in a City where there is abundance of Riches, but a great many Snares. If the minds of young Perſons be well diſpoſed that come hither, they may become <hi>great</hi> as well as <hi>good,</hi> from the ſmalleſt, or rather no beginning. It were endleſs to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the great Eſtates with which poor <hi>Orphans, Hoſpital-boys, Beggar-boys, Foundlings,</hi> and ſuch like, have been bleſſed in this City, and the Good that they have done in the World, whoſe minds have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to that which is good and honeſt. But on the other hand, where inclinations prevail to that which is evil, there are innumerable Temptations ready to hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry young Men and Women to ſeveral ſorts of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Wickedneſs. That which <hi>I</hi> ſhall only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at preſe is <hi>Theft;</hi> a Sin which hath alwaies been in the World, but <hi>I</hi> have ſome reaſon to ſay, that it abounds more in this than many are aware of: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints may be made in the words of the Proph et <hi>Hoſea, c.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>The Thief cometh within, and troops of Robbers ſpoyl without.</hi> I do not intend to ſpeak of <hi>Theft</hi> at large, (all <hi>Deceit</hi> being a breach of the Eighth Commandment) but of that which is commonly called
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38137:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo. That I may do what in me lies to ſuppreſs this Evil, I will endeavour to ſhew,
<list>
                  <item>1. What this Sin is in its own nature.</item>
                  <item>2. The evil Concomitants of it.</item>
                  <item>3. The fatal Conſequences of it. And,</item>
                  <item>4. Give ſome Advice to young Perſons for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. What this Sin is in it ſelf. A moſt hateful Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, which every one is aſham'd to own, much more to juſtifie. No man that robs another, offers ſo great violence to <hi>him</hi> as he offers to himſelf: He breaks through the moſt forcible Convictions of his own mind, that Guard which God hath ſet upon the Soul of Man, to keep it from Deſtruction. That every one is to have his own, and that it ought not to be taken from him, is one of the firſt impreſſions on our minds, when we are little Children. To take away the Right of another, either ſecretly or openly, either by Theft or Robbery, (for I ſhall ſpeak of them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly) is ſo low and ſo baſe a thing, that though the Devil can prevail with many wicked men ſo far as to be guilty of it, in hope of concealment, yet he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not harden any ſo, as not to be confounded when they are diſcovered; <hi>The Thief is aſhamed when he is found, Jer.</hi> 2.26. There needs no Bible to ſhew him his Sin; the moſt ſavage Heathen in the World can tell him, That it is to be abandon'd and abhorr'd; and the Thief knows, that he is worſe than that Heathen. <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> have ſhewed the groſſeſt Severities againſt this Sin. Hiſtory tells us of men that have been put to death for ſtealing an Apple, or a Bunch of Grapes, or ſome ſuch contemptible thing, probably from this Principle, That he who is broke looſe from his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to ſteal that which is of ſmall, may ſoon come to take away that which is of great account. It was not, that the Life of a Man was not valued by them; for they were no leſs ſevere to a falſe Accuſer. We read
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38137:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a Commander, to whom a Woman complain'd, That one of his Souldiers had ſtolen and eaten ſome of her Milk: The Souldier thereupon was put to death, and his Stomach ript open, that if the Milk were not there, the Woman might ſuffer death for her falſe Accuſation; if it were, ſhe ſhould have ſatisfaction for it, beſides the Life of the Offender, and ſo it proved. The Thief is one that un-mans himſelf, that he may become a hated Beaſt of Prey. Some ſay, that the reaſon why God forbad his People <hi>Iſrael</hi> eating Fowls of Prey, <hi>Levit.</hi> 11.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was, that they might not prey upon one another. More of the baſeneſs of this Sin will neceſſarily follow under other heads.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Conſider the evil Concomitants of <hi>Theft.</hi> As a Man, ſo a Sin is commonly-known by its Companions. The hainouſneſs of this Sin may be known by thoſe that keep it company. I will not undertake to mention all of them. When men break looſe from the firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of common Honeſty, it may well be expected, that the Devil ſhould ſo far prevail with them, as to ſtick at nothing that is wicked. I will therefore only mention ſome of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Lying.</hi> This is ſo well known, that it is become a Proverb, <hi>He that will steal will lye:</hi> The ſhame of that calls to this to ſhelter and protect it. A Lyar is abominable to God, who hath declared, that Hell ſhall be his Portion. I may mention one place amongſt many, becauſe there is a particular Note in it of God's diſpleaſure againſt that Sin, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.8. <hi>The fearful</hi> (<hi>i. e</hi> thoſe that deny their Religion, for fear of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution) <hi>and unbelieving, and the abominable, and murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and whoremongers, and ſorcerers, and idolaters, and all lyars ſhall have their part in the lake which burns with fire and brimstone. All Lyars,</hi> which ſeems to intimate, that though ſome of the other ſinners ſhould eſcape, yet the Lyar ſhall not. Or rather it may have rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſeveral ſorts of Lyars that are in the world;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38137:6"/>of which it is not to my preſent purpoſe to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: Moſt certainly it denotes to us, that the God of Truth hates, and will ſeverely puniſh Lyars.</p>
            <p>It is a Sin that is abominable to men too, for it is the bane of all Traffique, Converſe and Society. It is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of the very end of Speech: For to what purpoſe ſhould men ſpeak to one another, if what they ſay cannot be believ'd? But to the Thief, Lying is a thing in courſe of which his hardened Conſcience takes little notice: I queſtion whether he ever thinks to ask God forgiveneſs for it, or whether he thinks he ſhall need to do it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Blood-ſhedding.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Nahum</hi> charges theſe three upon <hi>Nineveh, c.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Wo to the bloody City, it is full of Lyes and Robbery.</hi> I wiſh there were not cauſe for ſuch a denunciation againſt our City.</p>
            <p>Thieves are very barbarous and inhumane: The Life of a man ſignifies little or nothing to them, if he offers to keep that which is his own from theſe men of Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; of which every year produces inſtances. The man (in the Parable, <hi>Luk</hi> 10.) might expect pity from the Paſſengers; but there is no mention of any that was to be expected from the Thieves: <hi>They stripped him, they wounded him, and they left him half dead.</hi> There is a Cruelty which they are guilty of, which is a kind of Murder by conſequence; and that is their robbing the poor and needy. The Son of <hi>Syrach</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 34.22. <hi>He that taketh away his Neighbour's living, ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him: and he that defraudeth the Labourer of his hire, is a blood-ſhedder.</hi> The poor man who hath gotten a little Mony to buy Bread for his Family, is as ſoon way-laid and robb'd as he that hath abundance. The Labourer, that carries home that which he <hi>earnes with the ſweat of his Brow,</hi> ſhall loſe it in the time of his <hi>ſweet ſleep,</hi> if the <hi>Thief can break in and ſteal it.</hi> He is ſo far from obſerving that Goſpel-Precept, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Let him that stole, steal no more: but let him labour, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38137:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>with his hands,</hi> &amp;c. That he is reſolved not only to continue ſtealing, but to ſteal from him who doth <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with his hands.</hi> This is ſuch a Cruelty, as may fitly come under this head of <hi>Murder;</hi> for it is to take away the Bread of the needy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs.</hi> Adultery and Fornication are the common ſins which Thieves are guilty of. I ſhould not have mentioned this, nor indeed have thought of it, if I had not very good ground for it, from the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of condemned Malefactors. They are a lewd Society of Men and Women, who having broke looſe from Honeſty, do not at all value Chaſtity. That only which they are afraid of, is the poyſoning of one anothers Bodies; yet this, it ſeems, is very common too (which by the way might be a good Argument to all young Men, to beware of thoſe filthy-diſeaſed Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which walk the ſtreets in the night-time, on purpoſe to entice Men into their dangerous Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, robbing their Souls, Bodies and Purſes at the ſame time) When once Men and Women forſake the common Principles of mankind, and become Beaſts of prey, it is no wonder if like Beaſts they be in common one with another.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Profane Swearing and Curſing.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariah, c.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. ſpeaks of the Judgment of God <hi>cutting off the Thief and the Swearer;</hi> Surely then when they both meet in one and the ſame perſon, he may well expect to be cut off. We ſeldome hear of any High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Robberies, but we hear how deſperately the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſwear and curſe; how they call to God for Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and ſince he doth not preſently ſend it, they make haſte to it by their ſpeed to the Gallows. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.24. <hi>Whoſo is Partner with a Thief, hateth his own Soul: he heareth curſing, and bewrayeth it not.</hi> By <hi>Curſing</hi> we may underſtand as many do, thoſe blaſphemous Speeches which are wont to come out of the mouths of Thieves. And if he that is Partner with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38137:7"/>a Thief, his Soul be in ſuch Danger, in what Danger is the Soul of the Thief himſelf? The great Evil of the Sin of <hi>prophane Swearing,</hi> may be the ſubject of another Tract. In the mean while, it may be enough to ſay, that it is ſuch an impudent daring of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, that we may wonder how he that is guilty of it, can ever expect to be in the favour of that God. Theſe are ſuch Concomitants of Theft, as may make all young perſons, afraid of it, leſt they wholly <hi>forſake God, and be forſaken of him.</hi> I proceed to conſider,</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Conſequents of Theft. There ſhould be an end propounded to every action, and every one ſhould conſider whether the enſuing diſadvantages will not out-weigh all the advantages that can be hoped for. But the Thief muſt be a man void of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and one in whom nothing but Deſperate Folly and Madneſs bears ſway; for he makes the worſt choice of any man living, and in a ſhort time muſt neceſſarily conclude, that the miſerableſt Beggar that is honeſt, is better than he. He hath little reaſon to be Proud, or to rejoyce in his Undertaking; for it is that which many Beggars refuſe, as being too baſe and vile. I ſhall conſider the Conſequences of it in three reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It brings intolerable Pain and Uneaſineſs to the Mind. There have been many inſtances, which ſhew that the Conſcience of a Thief is not ſo faſt aſleep as many honeſt men that are robbed by him; Nor can they bind that ſo faſt from ſtirring, and crying, <hi>[Thief]</hi> as ſometimes they bind thoſe that are awake. The Thief goes up and down the World with a Curſe very like to <hi>Cain</hi>'s; he is afraid that <hi>every one that meets him ſhould lay hold on him,</hi> in order to the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of his Life. The fear and terror of Thieves is excellently deſcribed by <hi>Job,</hi> as well as their wicked Trade, <hi>Job</hi> 24 16, 17. <hi>In the dark they dig through houſes, which they had marked for themſelves in the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38137:7"/>they know not the light. For the morning is to them even as the ſhadow of Death; if one know them, they are in the terrors of the ſhadow of death.</hi> Their Employment in the day-time is, to find out a Houſe which they may rob in the night: And in robbing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they rob themſelves of their peace and quiet. When the Day comes, they cannot ſay, that they <hi>care not who knows them:</hi> for if there be but <hi>one</hi> that knows them, they are preſently <hi>in the terrors of the ſhadow of Death:</hi> they are ſtruck with Fear, as a Man whom Death doth ſuddenly ſurprize or overſhadow. <hi>Theft</hi> is a prodigious folly as well as wickedneſs; for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ſtolen Goods are worth, they cannot anſwer the fear and terror which immediately follows, and is of long continuance. I was (many years ſince) a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator at the Execution of an Old Man, who (as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd too late) ſuffer'd wrongfully. As he proteſted his Innocency, relating to that for which he was Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, (other Thieves had thrown the ſtolen Goods un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Shop where he lay aſleep) ſo he confeſs'd, That when he was a young Man, he ſtole a Handkerchief from a Hedge, which was a trouble to him all the days of his Life. He added, That he alwaies thought he ſhould be hang'd, becauſe of that Handkerchief. It was a ſmall Theft that he was guilty of; but the trouble of his mind was very great, and the fear of God's Juſtice a continued Terror.</p>
            <p>I ſhall mention one more amongſt many, which I had from a Condemned Malefactor, by which it appears, that the terrors of death do ſometimes take hold on Thieves, and will not let them go, though none know them. One of the Gang was on a ſudden ſurpriz'd with a terrible apprehenſion that he ſhould be taken, tho' he had not heard of any Purſuit or Warrant that was againſt him: He diſcovered his fear to this Perſon, and withal told him, that he knew he ſhould be executed, and that he ſhould, upon his Examination, diſcover
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38137:8"/>him and the reſt of his Companions. He was deſired if he could not otherwiſe be rid of his Fears, to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas: but he replyed, that he had not power to do it. Hereupon, in a private Conſult, they reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be his Executioners; and ſo they were, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving perſwaded him on to the Water about midnight they there drown'd him. Thus we ſee how fear and folly is the conſequent of Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>The Perſon from whom I had this Account told me that he was the chief Actor in it; and that it had been an unſpeakable trouble to him; and the greater, becauſe the poor man begg'd ſo hard for Mercy, when they threw him out of the Boat. He likewiſe diſcovered a Remarkable Paſſage, which was the conſequent of his Murder. He ſoon heard of the dead Body of a Man waſh'd up at <hi>Westminster;</hi> and although he was terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly afraid, that if he ſaw it, the Corps would bleed, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there would ſomewhat happen, which would be tray him; yet he could not forbear going to ſee if it were the ſame Perſon; but it prov'd to be another. It is impoſſible that a Thief can think of any thing ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as a Jayl and the Gallows, Hell and Deſtruction How then can his mind be at eaſe?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider the Conſequence of <hi>Theft,</hi> in reference to outward Concerns.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a Sin which makes every man turn <hi>his</hi> Enemy who is guilty of it. I may ſay of the Thief as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith of other Perſons, <hi>They pleaſe not God, and are contrary to all men.</hi> It is a Sin ſo abominable, that ſo far as any are ſuſpected to be guilty of it, they are abhorr'd. The day of their Execution is a joyful day to the World. Thieves are not only hated of good men, but they are ſuch vile Servants of the Devil, a are hated of all their fellow-Servants. Thoſe that are moſt wicked in other reſpects, hate a Thief. The World ever cryed out againſt them. In <hi>Job</hi>'s time, who is ſuppos'd to have lived before <hi>Moſes,</hi> there was crying
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38137:8"/>after a Thief, <hi>Job</hi> 30.5. and our Saviour's Expreſſion, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.48. ſuppoſes that Men are alwaies ready with Swords and Staves to take a Thief. They muſt needs be hated, becauſe men are alwaies afraid of them, left their. Shops ſhould be robb'd in the day, and their Pockets pick'd; or, that their Houſes ſhould be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the night; and therefore there muſt be Bolts and Bars. Thieves are like the Devil, that go up and down, <hi>ſeeking whom they may devour.</hi> They are ſuch Plagues to the World, that our Saviour tells us, Heaven is a place of Happineſs, becauſe there are none there; <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.20. <hi>Lay up for your ſelves Treaſures in heaven, where thieves cannot break through and steal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Under this head I may conſider what a Thief is to all his honeſt Relations: Such <hi>a ſhame!</hi> that it is great incivility to ſpeak of him in their company, or ſo much as to mention his Name, if ſtrangers be preſent. If he hath a <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mother,</hi> Who can find words or courage to expreſs their heart-breaking grief and ſorrow? They wiſh a thouſand times that <hi>he</hi> had never been born, nor <hi>themſelves</hi> neither. Nothing in this World can afford comfort to them, which bears any propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their grief; ſo that if there were not a God to ſupport, it might well be expected that Diſtraction or Death ſhould ſeize upon them. I once ſaw, at an Aſſizes, a Thief condemned, who was no ſooner taken from the Bar, but his Mother ſtept up; the poor Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would fain have ſpoken to the Judge, and could not; but by the beating and wringing of her Hands, her diſtracted Countenance, and other Evidences of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable grief, ſhe melted both Judge and Juſtices and many hundreds more, into Tears. What is there in all the Gains of Wickedneſs, which can make amends to Parents for that ſorrow which they endure, when they conſider with what Charge, Care and Paines they preſerved a Life, which muſt be taken away by an Executioner? Little do young Perſons think, when
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38137:9"/>they take Evil courſes, what a <hi>Grief</hi> they are, or may be to <hi>their Father,</hi> and what <hi>a bitterneſs to her that bare them, Prov.</hi> 17.25.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Theft</hi> is a Sin which hath the moſt manifeſt curſe following it. Thieves of all men, have reaſon to ſay, that <hi>Treaſures of wickedneſs profit nothing:</hi> How many ſoever they ruin, they do not enrich themſelves. 'Tis ſeldome that Felons Goods amount to any thing that is conſiderable, unleſs they have been newly taken. What they get wickedly, they commonly ſpend wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſpeedily. Doubtleſs it coſt; them a great deal of Money in rioting, that they may drown the voice of their Conſciences, and forget how ſorrowful they have made others. They are at great Charge, it may be, in keeping Confederates, and engaging them in their aſſiſtance: Beſides, they are not of ſettled Habitations, but are running up and down, and muſt not value Charge, ſo they can but hope for ſafety and farther op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of doing miſchief. Thus they ſpend what they get, and only leave their Cloathes to him that rids the World of them. Their condition is deſcribed, <hi>Job</hi> 24.18. <hi>He is ſwift as the waters; their portion is accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on the earth, and they know not the way of the Vineyards. He is ſwift as the Waters;</hi> he runs like a violent ſtream, being hurried by his fear and danger. <hi>Their portion,</hi> this Clauſe is plural, though the other was not, denoting (ſay ſome) the univerſality of the Curſe. How many ſoever there are of them, and how much ſoever they get, <hi>their Portion (i. e.</hi> whatever they have) <hi>is accurſed on the earth. They behold not the way of the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards.</hi> To <hi>behold,</hi> frequently ſignifies to <hi>ſee</hi> with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: <hi>Vineyards</hi> are places of Profit and Pleaſure; and, I conceive, the meaning is, that they are a curſed Crew, that enjoy no good in the World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I will conſider the Thief, in reference to another World. It may ſeem <hi>ſtrange,</hi> conſidering the Nature and Concomitants of this Sin, that thoſe that are guilty
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38137:9"/>of it ſhould not be Atheiſts; and yet the contrary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in many of them. A notorious Robber told me, That he never doubted of a God, but hoped by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance at laſt to gain his Favour; and we find the vileſt of them as ſenſible then of a Soul departing, as of a Body dying. And it may ſeem no leſs ſtrange, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have been ſo deſperately wicked, they ſhould expect forgiveneſs from God, when they can be ſo no longer; and yet they diſcover great confidence of it. But it will appear, that their Caſe is very deſperate, if we conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. When it is that they repent. One would think, that ſo ſoon as a Thief comes into Priſon, the terrors of his Conſcience ſhould lay hold on him, and that he ſhould conſider that the Profit or Pleaſure of his Sin cannot compenſate that miſerable confinement, and the ſhame of appearing at the Bar of Juſtice, though he ſhould eſcape with his Life: But he is ſo hardened in his Wickedneſs, that it is in vain for a Miniſter, or any other, to ſpeak to him of the concern of his Soul, whilſt he hath any Hope that he ſhall eſcape the death of his Body. He will not endure to hear of it ſo long as there is hopes that he may continue his Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>It is, it ſeems, a common practice, if a Miniſter comes to ſpeak with one whom he knows not, to ſend ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to perſonate him, that when he is gone, they may make merry at the Relation of what he ſaid, and his diſappointment. I had ſuch a Trick put upon me when I went to viſit one (at the Requeſt of his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) who was executed ſoon after it. Good Counſel is but the occaſion of mockery to many of them, till they are ſure they ſhall be executed, and are within a little of it. They are ſo deſperately wicked, that they will keep their Hand in ure, by ſtealing in the Priſon, if there be opportunity for it. I once viſited a ſick Priſoner, whoſe near Relation had ſent him a Bottle of Cordial Water, and whilſt he aroſe from the ground
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38137:10"/>to ſpeak to me, his Bottle, upon which he laid his Head was ſtolen from him. The time of that Man's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance was not yet come, and therefore he continued ſtealing in that place; from whence he might expect ſhortly to be carried to the place of Execution.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider what a Thiefs repentance is, when it comes, and when he can ſtay no longer. He is under a great conſternation of mind to think of the wrath of God, and therefore he calls with great vehemency to him to have mercy upon him, all which may be done without any grief or ſorrow for the baſeneſs of his ſin. Doubtleſs, his Conſcience may tell him at the ſame time that he is not ſo ſorry for what he hath done, as he is, that the Gallows will hinder him from doing ſo any longer. He thinks that repentance conſiſts in nothing elſe, but the confeſſing of his ſin to God, and his begging Mercy and Pardon from him; and if this were all, there were very little difficulty indeed in being ſaved; avery little ſeeking would find the Kingdom of Heaven; No man ſhould need to doubt of Salvation, unleſs he dyed ſo ſuddenly, that he could not ſpeak a few words to God, or were at that time depriv'd of his Reaſon and Underſtanding: and if he were ſo, the preſumptuous Sinner would make no great matter of it, for he would conclude it to be a very hard thing, that God ſhould deſtroy a man for ever, becauſe he could not ſpeak to him before he dyed, that he might ask his Pardon, which he all along intended to do when he could of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him no more. By theſe and ſuch like pitiful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions doth the Devil ſecure to himſelf the Souls of theſe poor Creatures, who underſtand the myſtery of iniquity, but will not underſtand that which is moſt reaſonably and moſt plainly required of them, in order to their forgiveneſs and acceptance of God. Theſe two things are of abſolute neceſſity, which they conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Every Sinner muſt have the Grace and holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38137:10"/>of God <hi>to renew his mind,</hi> or elſe he cannot have the mercy of God to <hi>forgive his Sin.</hi> However, the <hi>fear of God,</hi> and of his diſpleaſure, may be <hi>the beginning of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> yet it is not the finiſher of it; for then a man might be ſaved, though he never loved God and that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> which is in God: A man might then go to Heaven without any preparation for it; 'tis enough to entitle him to it, that he is afraid of Hell.</p>
            <p>When the ſinner fearing puniſhment, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his evil actions, but becauſe of his evil mind, in which he finds an <hi>enmity against the Laws of God,</hi> doth not only implore the mercy of God, but his, Grace and Holy Spirit, to change his mind into a hatred of all his former wicked ways, and a delight in all that is good, this makes his condition hopeful, and ſhews that <hi>the fear of God</hi> was in him <hi>the beginning of wiſdom, (i. e.)</hi> of Holineſs and Goodneſs; and if this were the caſe of the worſt Thief in the world, it might be hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful too. But for a Thief to beg mercy from God, is no more an Argument of his Repentance and Amendment, than is his begging favour from the Judge, or his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don from the King. There is great difference between the reaſon of the King's pardoning and of God's. The King pardons from his Princely compaſſion, in hopes of Amendment; but God doth not pardon, unleſs he ſees amendment by a new Principle in the Heart and Mind of the Sinner: And therefore it is of infinite mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for every guilty Sinner to examine himſelf whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be ſuch a new Principle in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In caſes of injury done to Men, there is no mercy to be obtained from God, unleſs there be reſtitution of the wrong done, or all that is in the Sinners power to do towards it. The Offender hath no reaſon to expect that his Prayers ſhould be accepted of God, till he hath done this in order to it; <hi>If thy Brother hath ought againſt thee, firſt reconcile thy ſelf to thy Brother, Mat.</hi> 5.24. How can any Man think that God who requires <hi>Love to our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38137:11"/>Neighbour, doing good</hi> to him, and relieving of him, can be reconciled to <hi>him,</hi> who hath ſpent his time in <hi>doing hurt</hi> to his Neighbour, and never made any Reſtitution or Acknowledgment to him? It is ſtrange that any man can be ſo deluded as to think that he can rob his Neighbour, and keep his Goods from him, and then have Forgiveneſs from God. This were to ſuppoſe that God proffers Mercy to Sinners without their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Laws of Juſtice and Uprightneſs. There muſt be great ignorance in the Thief, or elſe it were impoſſible for him to think that God, who hath throughout the Scriptures declar'd his extream diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt all injuſtice and unrighteouſneſs, the Old Teſtament ſtrictly requiring Reſtitution from Thieves, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. and other places, and giving an account of temporal Judgments for oppreſſion or wrong done between man and man, as in <hi>Amos c.</hi> 4. and many other places: And the New Teſtament declaring, that the day of Judgment will be a day of Tryal of what Men have been to one another in the World; in which, God will caſt them <hi>into everlaſting puniſhment,</hi> that did not give to others; much more them that took away the Right of others, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. I ſay, that if the Thief were not ſtrangely ignorant, he could not think to expect Mercy from God, till he had done all that is in his power of Right to them whom he had wronged. If the Conſcience of the Sinner were rightly ſenſible, it would fly in his face when he begs Mercy from God, and tell him, that he hath not ſent word to this or that man, where his Goods are, and where he may have them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: He would think that he hears <hi>GOD</hi> ſay to him, <hi>What haſt thou done? the voice of thy Brother crieth unto me, whom thou haſt injur'd; and canſt thou expect Mercy from me, who doſt refuſe to do that which is right to thy Brother?</hi> The Heathens have a truer Notion of God than theſe men. The <hi>Ninevites</hi> expected no mercy from God, till they <hi>turned from the violence that was in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38137:11"/>their hands;</hi> the meaning of which is, according to the beſt, if not all Expoſitors, that they would not keep, but reſtore that which they had wrongfully taken away.</p>
            <p>I will not enlarge upon this, having treated more at large upon it in another<note n="*" place="margin">of Reſtitution.</note> Publication. If the Thief be a true penitent, he will ſend to them whom he hath wronged, uſing his utmoſt <hi>endeavour</hi> to help them to that which he hath taken from them: If he cannot do it, his grief will be the greater, and he will moſt heartily beg their Pardon and their Prayers. And this, I am ſure, is the opinion of all Divines, of all Perſwaſions, ſounded upon the Holy Scriptures, and upon the higheſt Reaſon. I urge this the more, becauſe I lately had ſome diſcourſe with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſactors in the Priſon, who would not be convinced, that there is ſo much as Forgiveneſs to be asked from Men, whatever wrong have been done to them; alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which the Scribes ſpake when they cavill'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Saviour, <hi>Who can forgive ſins but God only? Mark</hi> 2.7. Not knowing or conſidering that in all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond-table ſins forgiveneſs is to be had from Men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is injury done to them as well as to God; for otherwiſe, why ſhould the Scripture ſpeak ſo much of mens forgiving one another, and our Saviour direct us to pray, <hi>Forgive us as we forgive others?</hi> This For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs is not expected where the perſon offending doth not at leaſt acknowledge the offence, and declare his grief for it. <hi>If thy Brother treſpaſs against thee, if he repent, forgive him: And if he treſpaſs againſt thee ſeven times in a day, and ſeven times in a day turn again to thee, ſaying, I repent, forgive him, Luk.</hi> 17.3, 4. As God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires forgiveneſs from the Perſon offended, ſo he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, that the Perſon offending ſhould repent (<hi>i. e.</hi> declare his ſorrow) and ask forgiveneſs from him whom he hath injur'd; <hi>If he turn unto thee, ſaying, I repent, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him.</hi> I have heard Malefactors beg very loud of God to forgive them, but I have ſeldom heard any La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38137:12"/>that they have done ſo much Miſchief to honeſt and innocent Perſons. They think, and I have heard them ſay, that if they ſuffer for what they have done, it is a ſufficient ſatisfaction to all whom they have robbed, and therefore they need not concern themſelves any farther. Whereas on the contrary, it is only a ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Law, and none to them who have ſuffer'd the wrong, but rather a grief and trouble. I may add that of all condemned Malefactors, I have perceived leſs appearance of Repentance in Thieves than in any other, unleſs it be juſt at the time of Execution. I had once occaſion to obſerve a remarkable Penitent, who was condemned for <hi>Coyning:</hi> He ſpent his time in praying to God and uſing the moſt vehement and pathetical Eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations that ever <hi>I</hi> heard from any man; and the other Priſoners told me, that it was his practice day and night. But when <hi>I</hi> went in, and found <hi>him</hi> praying, <hi>I</hi> found the condemned Thieves ſleeping; and being awak'd, they were ſtill aſleep, as to any impreſſions that I could make upon them. They were as Stocks and Stones in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of that poor Penitent; but when they came to their Execution, they cried to God for mercy, which probably was all that they ever intended.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly.</hi> Thoſe that are true Penitents, are deſirous to promote Piety and Juſtice in the World, and to ſuppreſs Sin and Wickedneſs; both for the honour of God and of Religion; and likewiſe for the good and welfare of Mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If</hi> Thieves were Penitent, they would do what in them lies to ſuppreſs that wicked trade, which hath ſo diſhonoured <hi>God</hi> and the Chriſtian Religion, and hath taken away ſo many good mens Eſtates and bad mens Lives; they would particularly ſend to their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions to beg of them to forſake their ways and turn to God. But where ſhall we find any ſuch repentance in a Thief? <hi>I</hi> have great reaſon to ſay on the contrary from what <hi>I</hi> have heard in the Priſon, that many o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:38137:12"/>them wiſh good ſucceſs to their Companions, and that their wicked trade may thrive when they are executed.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>I</hi> have given a brief Account of the Repentance of theſe poor wretches, how ſhort it comes of that which is neceſſary for the Salvation of their Souls. <hi>I</hi> have no more reaſon to think that ſuch a man's Crying to God for Mercy, meerly for fear of Hell, avails him any thing, than that God hears the Prayers of the <hi>Wild Iriſh,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that when they go out to rob, they pray to God that they may find a good Booty. <hi>It</hi> is a Repentance without Piety or Juſtice, which can ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing. There is all <hi>Fear</hi> and no <hi>Love</hi> in it. <hi>I</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to give <hi>Advice to young perſons,</hi> for the <hi>Prevention of Theft.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Be careful to perform the Duties of Religion on the Lord's Day: it is commonly the firſt Complaint that Thieves make in the bitterneſs of their Souls, that they made the Lord's Day a day of <hi>Vanity</hi> and <hi>Idleneſs:</hi> From being at firſt only Sunday-walkers for their Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, they became at length Night walkers to their Deſtruction. Thoſe that at firſt only turn their Backs upon the Church, and will not ſerve God in it, come thither at length to ſerve the Devil in it; <hi>I</hi> mean, to pick Pockets and rob thoſe that are doing their Duties to God. God ſaith to the wicked Jews, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Will ye ſteal,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſtand before me in mine houſe?</hi> But we have wicked wretches, who make God's Houſe a place to ſteal <hi>in.</hi> Thoſe that are careful to obſerve the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God on that day, keep from ſuch horrid wickedneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Take heed of evil Principles and Opinions in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion. Thieves are often deluded with a Conceit that the Gallows is deſtin'd for them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was unavoidable. <hi>I</hi> knew a poor wretched Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the Country, who being blam'd for his thieving, and admoniſh'd to live an honeſt and induſtrious Life, anſwer'd, That he alwaies thought it was ordained
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38137:13"/>that he ſhould be hang'd; and therefore continued his Practice till he was ſo indeed, and ſeem'd to have then ſome kind of Support from it.</p>
            <p>And at the laſt Execution which I ſaw, there was a notorious Robber (who dyed of another Religion) whoſe condition I lamented, as he paſſed by me in the Priſon, and he told me, that he hoped he ſhould ſubmit with Patience, to that death which God had appointed for him. This is blaſphemouſly to ſuppoſe that God is the Author of <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> and a cruel Enemy to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Creature: it plainly ſhews the deluſion of the Devil.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Take heed of Apoſtatizing from the Beginings of a Religious Life: Early Obedience to God is the beſt Security of Happineſs both in this world, and that which is to come; and it is very rare, that thoſe who have been ſincerely careful to pleaſe God, do turn from it; and yet ſometimes it is ſo; and then ſuch perſons, forſaking God, do oft-times run into wicked and deſperate Courſes. Of this there was one inſtance ſome years ſince, of which I think fit to give as exact an Account as my Memory can retain, and in his own words, who was both a Thief and a Murderer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I was</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>when I was young, one that was well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the things of Religion: I was not only careful to frequent the publick Worſhip of God, but afraid to commit a ſecret Sin, or to omit a ſecret Duty: But the Diſputes that were about Religion made me doubt whether I was</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Right way; and not knowing where to ſerve God beſt, I grew remiſs and negligent. After that, I fell to Gaming; and having loſt Mony by it, I liſtened to thoſe that gave me wicked Counſel. After I came into the Priſon, for the ſpace of Fourteen days and nights I thought my ſelf in Hell, ſo great were the tortures of my Conſcience. I remembred almoſt every circumstance relating to my former care to ſerve God: What Miniſters I heard, what Texts, and how the Sermons affected me; and concluded that ſuch an Apoſtate could never obtain Mercy from God. After thoſe Fourteen
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38137:13"/>days were expired, my Deſpair began to abate, and then (which was about Four days before my Tryal) I ſpent my time day and night in crying to God to have mercy upon me, and was heard by him, for I found his Holy Spirit comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of me with aſſurance of the Pardon of my Sin: And I bleſs God, the Sentence of Death was not terrible to me; and I queſtion not, but I ſhall have Comfort at my Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the ſame God.</hi> An inſtance which ſhews how dangerous it is for young Perſons not to perſevere in the practice of Religion, and how infinitely merciful God is to thoſe that are truly and ſincerely penitent.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Take heed of Idleneſs. <hi>Agurs</hi> Prayer is, That God would not give him Poverty, leſt (being poor) he ſteal, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.9. As ſome men are poor by the Providence of God, ſo others make themſelves poor by their own ſlothfulneſs; which is an in-let to this Sin, that brings them to Deſtruction. God did not intend that Man ſhould be idle in the ſtate of innocency; nor are the glorified Beings idle in the ſtate of Happineſs. And the truth is, Man is a Creature to whom idleneſs is irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and therefore when wicked men will not be ſet to lawful Work, there's an Enemy that will employ them in that which is unlawful.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Be not fickle and unconſtant, but fix to that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, to which the Providence of God doth prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally direct. Many men diſliking their Trades and Educations, make tryals of that which they underſtand not, and that brings them to the trade of Stealing at laſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Be frugal.</hi> When young perſons addict themſelves to the gratifying of a profuſe and laviſh humour, it will be maintain'd, tho it be by ſtealing Mony when their own is gone. They are Thieves to themſelves in the firſt place; or, I may ſay, that <hi>Luſt</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> robs <hi>them,</hi> and then they rob others.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Take heed of ſmall Beginnings in that which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. Thoſe Servants that give little things out of the Shop, which they know their Maſters will not allow of, or out of the Kitchin, without the leave of their Miſtris,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38137:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>(which none but idle and bad People will receive) come by degrees to more notorious Acts of wickedneſs: Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little unjuſt action weakens the defence of the mind, and breaks the bonds of uprightneſs and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>The certain way for young-men to avoid this deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Wickedneſs, is, to obſerve the Apoſtles Rule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, <hi>to exerciſe themſelves alwaies,</hi> (wherever they are, ſeen or unſeen) <hi>to have a conſcience void of offence both towards God and towards men;</hi> and never to forget that Proverbial ſaying, which our Saviour makes uſe of, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16 10. <hi>He that is faithful in that which is leaſt, is faithful alſo in much: and he that is unjuſt in the least, is unjuſt alſo in much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now, the God of truth and Righteouſneſs,</hi> who is the Judge of all the Earth, and cannot but <hi>do right; and who will proceed in judgment according, to the rules of juſtice and uprightneſs; put his fear into the hearts of thoſe that have done wrong, that they may not offer to him a mock-Repentance, but really turn from their wicked ways, doing that which is right: And into the Hearts of yonng perſons, that they may never bring themſelves to miſery in this World, or eternal Torments in the next, but may live ſo as to be the beloved Diſciples of our Lord and Saviour</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38137:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
